Guide to the Julian Sorell Huxley Papers, 1899-1980 MS 050
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series XI: Clippings, 256478
  - Misc. Clippings, 1940-49; 256493 (Box 140, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Clippings, 1950-June 1953; 256492 (Box 140, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Clippings, July-December 1953; 256491 (Box 140, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Clippings, July-October 1953; 256490 (Box 140, Folder 5)
  - Misc. Clippings, January-June 1954; 256489 (Box 140, Folder 6)
  - Misc. Clippings, July-December 1954; 256488 (Box 140, Folder 7)
  - Misc. Clippings, 1955-59; 256487 (Box 140, Folder 8)
  - Misc. Clippings, 1960; 256486 (Box 141, Folder 1)
  - Misc. Clippings, 1961; 256485 (Box 141, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Clippings, 1962; 256484 (Box 141, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Clippings, 1963; 256483 (Box 141, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Clippings, 1964; 256482 (Box 141, Folder 5)
  - Misc. Clippings, 1965-66, 1969; 256481 (Box 141, Folder 6)
  - Misc. Clippings, 1970-74; 256480 (Box 141, Folder 7)
  - Misc. Clippings, n.d.; 256479 (Box 141, Folder 8)
- Series XII: Photographs and Visual Materials, 256344
  This contains photographs, slides, cartoons and sketches of the collection, as well as maps and Audubon bird prints. The collection spans Huxley's life and interests, including photographs of Eton school fellows, professional associates, colleagues and friends, and sketches of plant life, travels and expeditions. Of special interest are the photographs of Texas flora and fauna, the Oxford expedition to Spitsbergen, Huxley's several trips to Russia, and his later travels, first for Unesco and later as an expression of his own interests. There are also photographs of family members and friends, including a fine portrait of H.G. Wells, and several cartoons of Unesco figures, as well as many pictures recording animal behavior.
  One of the most beautiful portions of the series are the drawings made by Huxley. These drawings range in subject matter from biological drawings to sketches and doodles. There are also one or two landscapes in pencil and some lovely drawings of plants.
  There are also numerous miscellaneous photographs of people and places, as well as slides either taken by Huxley or sent to him by friends or colleagues.
  The photographs and visual materials are arranged according to subject matter rather than in chronological order, and care has been taken to leave together photographs which arrived at this archive in groups.
  - Eton friends, 1900-1906; 256477 (Box 142, Folder 1)
  - Eton friends, 1900-1906; 256476 (Box 142, Folder 2)
  - Eton friends, 1900-1906; 256475 (Box 142, Folder 3)
  - Eton friends, 1900-1906; 256474 (Box 142, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. T. H. Huxley, 256473 (Box 142, Folder 5)
  - Francis Albert Eley Crew, 256472 (Box 142, Folder 6)
  - N. T. Huxley, 256471 (Box 142, Folder 7)
  - Young Man (Oxford), 256470 (Box 142, Folder 8)
  - Reinhard Dohrn family, 1910; 256469 (Box 142, Folder 9)
  - German Courtyard, 1906?; 256468 (Box 142, Folder 10)
  - Country house, 1890-1910?; 256467 (Box 142, Folder 11)
  - Portrait of a young woman, 256466 (Box 142, Folder 12)
  - Castle in the Neckar Valley, 1909; 256465 (Box 142, Folder 13)
  - Geoffrey Smith, 1912; 256464 (Box 142, Folder 14)
  - Jelly d'Aranyi, 1913; 256463 (Box 142, Folder 15)
  - Boyd Simmons, Houston, Texas, 1915; 256462 (Box 142, Folder 16)
  - Texas plants, 1914; 256461 (Box 142, Folder 17)
  - Postcards, California, 1915; 256460 (Box 142, Folder 18)
  - "Floyd Dell in New England", 256459 (Box 142, Folder 19)
  - H. Spemann, 256458 (Box 142, Folder 20)
  - Woods Hole, Mass., 1916; 256457 (Box 142, Folder 21)
  - WWI, Italy, 256456 (Box 142, Folder 22)
  - WWI Photographs, 256455 (Box 142, Folder 23)
  - Early photos, Crested Grebe, 1919; 256454 (Box 142, Folder 24)
  - Party in Hungary, 1920s; 256453 (Box 142, Folder 25)
  - G. P. Wells, 1920s; 256452 (Box 142, Folder 26)
  - Tom Longstaff, Spitzbergen, 1921; 256451 (Box 142, Folder 27)
  - A. C. Hardy, 1922; 256450 (Box 142, Folder 28)
  - H. G. Wells, 256449 (Box 142, Folder 29)
  - Mae West, 1939; 256448 (Box 142, Folder 30)
  - Isaiah Bowman, 1940; 256447 (Box 142, Folder 31)
  - Kapp Unesco Drawings (photos), 1946; 256446 (Box 142, Folder 32)
  - Pugwash (people), 1955; 256445 (Box 142, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous (including family photos), 1956; 256444 (Box 142, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous, America Trip, Family and Friends, 1956; 256443 (Box 142, Folder 35)
  - Tom Longstaff and wife, 1950s; 256442 (Box 142, Folder 36)
  - Mimi Gielgud, France, contact proofs, 256441 (Box 142, Folder 37)
  - JSH and Griffith Evans, 1962; 256440 (Box 142, Folder 38)
  - King Hussein of Jordan, 1963; 256439 (Box 142, Folder 39)
  - 2 unidentified men, 256438 (Box 142, Folder 40)
  - Drawings by JSH, 256437 (Box 142, Folder 41)
  - Drawings, 256436 (Box 142, Folder 42)
  - Drawings, undated; 256435 (Box 142, Folder 43)
  - "Men of Science", 256434 (Box 142, Folder 44)
  - Jack Rosen caricature of JSH, October 1946; 256433 (Box 142, Folder 45)
  - JSH at Whipshade, 1940?; 256432 (Box 142, Folder 46)
  - JSH and Henry Moore, 1972; 256431 (Box 142, Folder 47)
  - JSH, 1972?; 256430 (Box 142, Folder 48)
  - 31 Pond Street, 1983?; 256429 (Box 142, Folder 49)
  - Spitzenbergen Expedition negatives, 1921; 256428 (Box 143, Folder 1)
  - Spitzenbergen Expedition, 1921; 256427 (Box 143, Folder 2)
  - Spitzenbergen Expedition, 1921; 256426 (Box 143, Folder 3)
  - Spitzenbergen Expedition, 1921; 256425 (Box 143, Folder 4)
  - Spitzenbergen Expedition, 1921; 256424 (Box 143, Folder 5)
  - Spitzenbergen Expedition, 1921; 256423 (Box 143, Folder 6)
  - Spitzenbergen Expedition, "Rutmark", 1921; 256422 (Box 143, Folder 7)
  - Russia, negatives, 256421 (Box 144, Folder 1)
  - Darwin Museum, Moscow, #1-30, 256420 (Box 144, Folder 2)
  - Darwin Museum, Moscow, #31-50, 256419 (Box 144, Folder 3)
  - Darwin Museum, Moscow, (1932, 1949), 1931, 1945?; 256418 (Box 144, Folder 4)
  - Darwin Museum, Moscow, #51-70, 1931; 256417 (Box 144, Folder 5)
  - Darwin Museum, Moscow, 1945; 256416 (Box 144, Folder 6)
  - Russia, Intourist Trip, 1931; 256415 (Box 144, Folder 7)
  - Russian photos, Intourist Trip, 1931; 256414 (Box 144, Folder 8)
  - Lysenko, Huxley, Ashby; USSR, 1945; 256413 (Box 144, Folder 9)
  - Moscow Museum, 1945; 256412 (Box 144, Folder 10)
  - Ireland, 1934; 256411 (Box 145, Folder 1)
  - Iceland, (negatives), 1949; 256410 (Box 145, Folder 2)
  - Iceland, 1949; 256409 (Box 145, Folder 3)
  - India, scenery, 1950; 256408 (Box 145, Folder 4)
  - India, animals, (negatives), 1952; 256407 (Box 145, Folder 5)
  - Syria, (negatives), 1952; 256406 (Box 145, Folder 6)
  - "Methodist Overseas Missions", Australia, 1952; 256405 (Box 145, Folder 7)
  - Persia, (negatives), 1953; 256404 (Box 145, Folder 8)
  - India, Moslem architecture, (negatives), 1953; 256403 (Box 145, Folder 9)
  - "Methodist Overseas Missions", Australia, 1953; 256402 (Box 145, Folder 10)
  - Heron Island, 1953; 256401 (Box 145, Folder 11)
  - Fiji, 1953; 256400 (Box 145, Folder 12)
  - Postcards from Iran, 1953; 256399 (Box 145, Folder 13)
  - Australia, 1953; 256398 (Box 145, Folder 14)
  - Baghdad Flood, (negative), 1953-54; 256397 (Box 145, Folder 15)
  - India, (slides and negatives), 1953-54; 256396 (Box 145, Folder 16)
  - Madras, 1953-54; 256395 (Box 145, Folder 17)
  - Australia, scenery, 1953-54; 256394 (Box 145, Folder 18)
  - Australia, "Works of Man", 1953-54; 256393 (Box 145, Folder 19)
  - Australia, animals, (negatives), 1953-54; 256392 (Box 145, Folder 20)
  - Australia, Aborigines, 1953-54; 256391 (Box 145, Folder 21)
  - Australia, 1953-54; 256390 (Box 145, Folder 22)
  - Unesco trip, 1953-54; 256389 (Box 145, Folder 23)
  - Thailand, 1954; 256388 (Box 145, Folder 24)
  - Philippines, scenery and general, 1954; 256387 (Box 145, Folder 25)
  - Mykonos, Christian Stathatos photos, 1958; 256386 (Box 145, Folder 26)
  - Africa, 1960s; 256385 (Box 145, Folder 27)
  - Africa, 256384 (Box 145, Folder 28)
  - Switzerland, France, 256383 (Box 145, Folder 29)
  - Mentone, 256382 (Box 145, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous travel photos, 1940s-1960s; 256381 (Box 145, Folder 31)
  - Jewelled termite slide and drawing, 256380 (Box 146, Folder 1)
  - Embryo, 256379 (Box 146, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous animal photos, 256378 (Box 146, Folder 3)
  - Snake mimicry by catepillar, Adaptation, 256377 (Box 146, Folder 4)
  - Canadian winter, 256376 (Box 146, Folder 5)
  - Misc., undated; 256375 (Box 146, Folder 6)
  - "Eritis sicut deus", 256374 (Box 146, Folder 7)
  - Postcards, 256373 (Box 146, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, magazine portraits, 256372 (Box 146, Folder 9)
  - Card from Maharaj and Maharami of Jhalawar, 256371 (Box 146, Folder 10)
  - John Skeaping Christmas Card, 256370 (Box 146, Folder 11)
  - Contact sheets and negatives, 256369 (Box 146, Folder 12)
  - Bird photos (negatives), 256368 (Box 146, Folder 13)
  - Map of British East Africa with Author's Route, 256367 (Box 146, Folder 14)
  - Maps, 256366 (Box 146, Folder 15)
  - "Photographs of the Lyrebird", 256365 (Box 146, Folder 16)
  - Audubon bird prints, 256364 (Box 146, Folder 17)
  - Differentiation, 1920s; 256363 (Box 146, Folder 18)
  - Postcards from USA, 1920s; 256362 (Box 146, Folder 19)
  - Baby experiment, 1928; 256361 (Box 146, Folder 20)
  - Christmas card, 1929; 256360 (Box 146, Folder 21)
  - "Walpurgisnacht", 194?; 256359 (Box 146, Folder 22)
  - "Life Magazine" article, 1952; 256358 (Box 146, Folder 23)
  - JSH on the cover of "Everybody's", 1957; 256357 (Box 146, Folder 24)
  - Plant photo, 1957; 256356 (Box 146, Folder 25)
  - Exhibition on the Kalinga Prize, 1960; 256355 (Box 146, Folder 26)
  - Arusha Conference, 1961; 256354 (Box 146, Folder 27)
  - U.S. Science Pavilion, Seattle World's Fair, 1962; 256353 (Box 146, Folder 28)
  - Galapagos Institute Scientific Project, 1960-66; 256352 (Box 146, Folder 29)
  - List of photos, 1966; 256351 (Box 146, Folder 30)
  - Pictures from Robin Best, 1973; 256350 (Box 146, Folder 31)
  - From Calvin Oakknoll, 1972; 256349 (Box 146, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous negatives, 256348 (Box 146, Folder 33)
  - "New Naturalist" autobiography, color negatives, 256347 (Box 146, Folder 34)
  - Ruth Page, 1916; 256346 (Box 146, Folder 35)
  - Negative cannisters, 256345 (Box 147)
- Series XIII: Memorabilia, 256317
  This series is by its nature the most miscellaneous and eclectic of the collection, for it contains both personal and professional souvenirs and mementos from 1910 until Huxley's death. These are arranged by decade in chronological order, and include playbills and concert programs, banquet menus, limericks and jokes, copies of legal documents, awards, citations and membership certificates, Christmas card and guest lists, and names and addresses of friends and associates.
  There is also a sampling of curiosities and souvenirs which were of interest to Huxley and kept by him: picture post cards, unusual advertisements, travel brochures and business cards.
  Series XV: BOX FILES also contains a large collection of picture post cards.
  - 1910-15, 256343 (Box 148, Folder 1)
  - 1916-19, 256342 (Box 148, Folder 2)
  - 1920s, 256341 (Box 148, Folder 3)
  - 1920s, 256340 (Box 148, Folder 4)
  - 1930s, 256339 (Box 149, Folder 1)
  - 1930s, 256338 (Box 149, Folder 2)
  - Undated, 256337 (Box 149, Folder 3)
  - 1940s, 256336 (Box 150, Folder 1)
  - 1940s, 256335 (Box 150, Folder 2)
  - Honors certificates, 1940s; 256334 (Box 150, Folder 3)
  - 1950s, 256333 (Box 151, Folder 1)
  - 1950s, 256332 (Box 151, Folder 2)
  - The Darwin Medal, 256331 (Box 151, Folder 3)
  - Diploma, University of Chicago, 1959; 256330 (Box 151, Folder 4)
  - Albert Lasker Award, 1959; 256329 (Box 151, Folder 5)
  - 1960s, 256328 (Box 152, Folder 1)
  - Cartoon, 1962; 256327 (Box 152, Folder 2)
  - 1963, 256326 (Box 152, Folder 3)
  - Contract, 1967; 256325 (Box 152, Folder 4)
  - List of colleagues to whom reprints were sent, 1960s; 256324 (Box 152, Folder 5)
  - 1970s, 256323 (Box 152, Folder 6)
  - 1970s, 256322 (Box 152, Folder 7)
  - Imperial College Exhibition catalogue, 1972; 256321 (Box 152, Folder 8)
  - Christmas card lists, 256320 (Box 152, Folder 9)
  - Undated material, 256319 (Box 152, Folder 10)
  - Oversized Materials: Unesco material; Clippings, Anatomical drawings; Memorabilia, AAAs; Early materials, travel material, 1946; 1916; 256318 (Box 153, Box 154)
- Series XIV: Box Files, 256203
  Sir Julian collected reprints, clippings, notes, lectures and correspondence and filed them by subject in his box files. These files were sold to a dealer in the 1970s who compiled a contents listing and rough name index for them (available on request). The listing also includes a biographical note and a general description of the file contents.
  Materials in the BOX FILES span the same dates as the core collection and are most numerous during the same period, 1940-1970. Of special note are notes on the Crested Grebe in the "Birds and Bird-Watching" file, the files on Russia and a collection of about 200 picture postcards.
  - Animal Behavior, General Invertebrates, 256316 (Box 155, Folder 1)
  - Animal Behavior, General Invertebrates, 256315 (Box 155, Folder 2)
  - Animal Behavior, General Invertebrates, 256314 (Box 155, Folder 3)
  - Animal Behavior, General Invertebrates, 256313 (Box 155, Folder 4)
  - Animal Behavior, General Invertebrates, 256312 (Box 155, Folder 5)
  - Animal Behavior, Vertebrates, 256311 (Box 156, Folder 1)
  - Animal Behavior, Vertebrates, 256310 (Box 156, Folder 2)
  - Assorted pamphlets and papers, 256309 (Box 157, Folder 1)
  - Assorted pamphlets and papers, 256308 (Box 157, Folder 2)
  - Behavior, Birds, 256307 (Box 158, Folder 1)
  - Behavior, Birds, 256306 (Box 158, Folder 2)
  - Behavior, Birds, 256305 (Box 158, Folder 3)
  - Behavior, Birds, 256304 (Box 158, Folder 4)
  - Behavior, Birds, 256303 (Box 158, Folder 5)
  - Behavior, Birds, 256302 (Box 158, Folder 6)
  - Behavior, Birds, 256301 (Box 158, Folder 7)
  - Behavior, Birds, 256300 (Box 158, Folder 8)
  - Behavior, Mammals, 256299 (Box 159, Folder 1)
  - Behavior, Mammals, 256298 (Box 159, Folder 2)
  - Behavior, Mammals, 256297 (Box 159, Folder 3)
  - Behavior, Mammals, 256296 (Box 159, Folder 4)
  - Behavior, Mammals, 256295 (Box 159, Folder 5)
  - Behavior, Man, 256294 (Box 160, Folder 1)
  - Behavior, Man, 256293 (Box 160, Folder 2)
  - Behavior, Man, 256292 (Box 160, Folder 3)
  - Behavior, Man, Neurology...etc., 256291 (Box 161, Folder 1)
  - Behavior, Man, Neurology...etc., 256290 (Box 161, Folder 2)
  - Behavior, Man, Neurology...etc., 256289 (Box 161, Folder 3)
  - Behavior, Man, Neurology...etc., 256288 (Box 161, Folder 4)
  - Birds and Birdwatching, 256287 (Box 162, Folder 1)
  - Birds and Birdwatching, 256286 (Box 162, Folder 2)
  - Birds and Birdwatching, letters, 256285 (Box 162, Folder 3)
  - Birds, Ecology, Migration, 256284 (Box 163, Folder 1)
  - Birds, Ecology, Migration, 256283 (Box 163, Folder 2)
  - Birds, Ecology, Migration, 256282 (Box 163, Folder 3)
  - Birds, Ecology, Migration, 256281 (Box 163, Folder 4)
  - Brain Neurology, 256280 (Box 164, Folder 1)
  - Brain Neurology, 256279 (Box 164, Folder 2)
  - Brain Neurology, 256278 (Box 164, Folder 3)
  - Cancer, 256277 (Box 164, Folder 4)
  - Cancer, 256276 (Box 164, Folder 5)
  - Cancer, 256275 (Box 164, Folder 6)
  - Culture, 256274 (Box 165, Folder 1)
  - Culture, 256273 (Box 165, Folder 2)
  - Culture, 256272 (Box 165, Folder 3)
  - Culture, 256271 (Box 165, Folder 4)
  - Education, 256270 (Box 166, Folder 1)
  - Education, 256269 (Box 166, Folder 2)
  - Education, 256268 (Box 166, Folder 3)
  - Education, 256267 (Box 166, Folder 4)
  - Ephemera, Postcards, 256266 (Box 167, Folder 1)
  - Ephemera, Postcards, 256265 (Box 167, Folder 2)
  - Ephemera, Postcards, 256264 (Box 167, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera, Postcards, 256263 (Box 167, Folder 4)
  - Epigenetics, 256262 (Box 167, Folder 5)
  - Epigenetics, 256261 (Box 167, Folder 6)
  - Epigenetics, 256260 (Box 167, Folder 7)
  - Genetics, 256259 (Box 168, Folder 1)
  - Genetics, 256258 (Box 168, Folder 2)
  - Genetics, 256257 (Box 168, Folder 3)
  - Genetics, 256256 (Box 168, Folder 4)
  - Genetics, 256255 (Box 168, Folder 5)
  - Groups, 256254 (Box 169, Folder 1)
  - Groups, 256253 (Box 169, Folder 2)
  - Groups, 256252 (Box 169, Folder 3)
  - Invertebrates, 256251 (Box 169, Folder 4)
  - Konrad Lorenz, 256250 (Box 169, Folder 5)
  - Konrad Lorenz, 256249 (Box 169, Folder 6)
  - "Envelope No. I", Letters to Huxley, 256248 (Box 170, Folder 1)
  - Life/Origin/Biochemistry, 256247 (Box 170, Folder 2)
  - Life/Origin/Biochemistry, 256246 (Box 170, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts, 256245 (Box 171, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts, 256244 (Box 171, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts, 256243 (Box 171, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts, "Soviet Genetics and World Science", 256242 (Box 171, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts, 256241 (Box 171, Folder 5)
  - Maps, 256240 (Box 172, Folder 1)
  - Music, published, 256239 (Box 173, Folder 1)
  - Pamphlets, 256238 (Box 174, Folder 1)
  - Pamphlets, 256237 (Box 174, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlets, 256236 (Box 174, Folder 3)
  - Pamphlets, 256235 (Box 174, Folder 4)
  - Pamphlets, 256234 (Box 174, Folder 5)
  - Lectures, "Lect. 2 Nat. Sel.", 256233 (Box 175, Folder 1)
  - Lectures, "Lecture 3", 256232 (Box 175, Folder 2)
  - Lectures, "Lecture 4", 256231 (Box 175, Folder 3)
  - Lectures, "Lecture 5", 256230 (Box 175, Folder 4)
  - Lectures, "Lecture 6", 256229 (Box 175, Folder 5)
  - Lectures, "Ghana Lecture 1", Aggrey-Fraser-Guggisberg Lecture, 256228 (Box 175, Folder 6)
  - Lectures, Aggrey-Fraser-Guggisberg Lectures (I-IV), 256227 (Box 175, Folder 7)
  - Lectures, "Patten Lectures", Lecture 1, 256226 (Box 175, Folder 8)
  - Lectures, Patten Lectures 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 256225 (Box 175, Folder 9)
  - Lectures, "Fawley Lecture", 256224 (Box 175, Folder 10)
  - Pamphlets, Russia, 256223 (Box 176, Folder 1)
  - Pamphlets, Russia, 256222 (Box 176, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlets, Russia, 256221 (Box 176, Folder 3)
  - Russia, 1931; 256220 (Box 176, Folder 4)
  - Moscow, 1931; 256219 (Box 176, Folder 5)
  - Russia, 1931; 256218 (Box 176, Folder 6)
  - Russia, 1931; 256217 (Box 176, Folder 7)
  - Selection, 256216 (Box 177, Folder 1)
  - Selection, 256215 (Box 177, Folder 2)
  - Selection, 256214 (Box 177, Folder 3)
  - Selection, 256213 (Box 177, Folder 4)
  - Speciation and Species, 256212 (Box 177, Folder 5)
  - Speciation and Species, 256211 (Box 177, Folder 6)
  - Speciation and Species, 256210 (Box 177, Folder 7)
  - Stabilization, 256209 (Box 178, Folder 1)
  - Stabilization, 256208 (Box 178, Folder 2)
  - Taxonomy Speciation, 256207 (Box 178, Folder 3)
  - Taxonomy Speciation, 256206 (Box 178, Folder 4)
  - Trends and Possibilities, 256205 (Box 179, Folder 1-2)
  - Inventory and information about Box files, 256204 (Box 180, Folder 1)